Finding Aid for Fletcher Family Papers, 1856-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fletcher Family Papers 1856-1936
Fletcher family.
851292 Aa 2
Family based in Detroit and Alpena, Michigan and engaged in many business enterprises; business records detailing involvement in lumbering, milling, paper manufacturing, and power and light companies, mainly in Alpena, Michigan.
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Ralph Fletcher (donor no. 4672 ) and came to the library in 1968.
The collection is open to research.
George N. Fletcher was founder of various business enterprises in Alpena, Michigan. He was born in Ludlow, Vermont on December 13, 1813. He subsequently moved with his parents to Ohio in 1832. He graduated from Oberlin College in 1840, then went to Boston where he worked as treasurer of the Old Colony Railroad, a position he held until 1850. Around this time, Fletcher, desiring new opportunities, began investigating the economic potential of lumbering. So with a partner James K. Lockwood, Fletcher scouted out and purchased timberland acreage in the area surrounding present-day Alpena, Michigan. The area had great potential with its riches of pine trees. Moving to Michigan in the mid-1850s, Fletcher decided to live in Detroit with his family though most of his business endeavors were in Alpena.
Fletcher began with the building of a dam and a saw mill on river nearby to his timber lands, then began the process of converting timber to lumber. Among the different companies that he controlled solely or with partners were Fletcher, Pack & Company, George N. Fletcher & Sons, and A. F. Fletcher & Co. As his sons matured, he began involving them, especially Frank W. Fletcher, in the operation of his businesses.
Frank W. Fletcher, born in Boston in 1853, grew up in Detroit, but unlike his father he would make Alpena his home. Graduating from the University of Michigan in 1875, he moved to the city in 1878 where he worked with the Fletcher, Pack & Company. In the 1880s, understanding that the once rich timber lands were dwindling, Frank Fletcher encouraged his father to look beyond the milling of lumber for new opportunities. He suggested the substitution of lumber milling with a new process of sulfide pulp manufacturing. This led in 1886 to the construction of a sulfide fiber mill, later followed in 1898 with a paper mill, the Fletcher Paper Company. Frank Fletcher also used to acumen to improve the growing city of Alpena itself, developing its water and power infrastructure. One result was the organization of the Alpena Power Company in 1905.
As an alumnus, Frank Fletcher was active in University of Michigan affairs. In 1894, he was appointed (later elected) to the University's Board of Regents, serving until 1910. He died in 1922.
The Fletcher family collection consists primarily the records of the family's business activities. The business correspondence date from 1856 to 1936 and relates to the operation of family firms, notably A. F. Fletcher & Co., Fletcher Pack & Co., and George N. Fletcher & Sons. The business records series is more specifically arranged by company name and includes the Alpena Power Company/Alpena Electric Light Co., George N. Fletcher & Sons, and the Alpena Water Company among others. Other series in the collection relate to both personal and corporate litigation. The Frank W. Fletcher Personal papers concerns his tenure as a regent of the University of Michigan and his continuing interest in university affairs.
Subjects:
A. F. Fletcher & Company (Alpena, Mich.); Alpena (Mich.); Alpena Electric Light Company (Mich.); Alpena Mill Company (Mich.); Alpena Power Company (Mich.); Alpena Sulphite Fibre Company (Mich.); Alpena Water Company (Mich.); Business records.; Electric industries.; Fletcher, Pack and Company (Alpena, Mich.); Fletcher Paper Company (Alpena, Mich.); Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; George N. Fletcher & Sons (Alpena, Mich.); Logging--Michigan--Alpena.; Lumbering--Michigan--Alpena.; Public utilities--Michigan.; Thunder Bay Boom Company (Alpena, Mich.); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Log driving--Michigan--Thunder Bay River.
Contributors:
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922.; Fletcher, George N., b. 1813.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.
Genre
Business records.
- Business correspondence 1856-1936
  The Business Correspondence series consists of letters of George N. Fletcher, Frank W. Fletcher, and the office correspondence of A.F. Fletcher & Co., Fletcher Pack & Co., and George N. Fletcher & Sons.
  - 1856-1859 (Box 1)
  - 1860s (Box 1)
  - 1872-1879 (Box 1)
  - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1892 (Box 1)
    (include letter, 1891, of Donald M. Dickinson)
  - 1894-1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1898 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1899 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1899 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1899 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1900 (Box 1)
  - April-July 1900 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - 1917 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1918 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1918 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1919 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1919 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1920 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1920 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1921 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1923 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924-1928, 1930, 1936 (Box 1)
- Business records
  The Business Records series contains files of, or relating to, specific Fletcher enterprises.
  - Rumford Falls Power Co., Portland, Maine papers 1891-1898 (Box 2)
  - Alpena Power Company/Alpena Electric Light Co.
    - Business correspondence
      - 1905-1906 (Box 2)
      - 1907-1908 (Box 2)
      - 1909 (Box 2)
      - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
      - 1912-1913 (Box 2)
      - 1914-1917 (Box 2)
    - Letter book 1906-1909 (Box 2)
    - Minute book 1913 (Box 2)
  - Ox Bow Farm Company, Alpena, Michigan
    - Papers
      - 1912-1915 1925-1929 (Box 2)
      - 1930 (Box 2)
      - 1931 (Box 2)
      - 1932 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - MacManus Company, Detroit (advertising agency)
    - Papers 1912-1914 (Box 2)
    - Papers 1915-1917 (Box 2)
  - Alpena Mill Company
    - Ledger 1864 (Box 2)
  - Alpena Water Company
    - Record book #1 1878-1898 (Box 2)
  - American Sulphite Fibre and Paper Co. Record book 1886-1889 (Box 2)
  - Alpena Sulphite Fibre Co. Letter book 1907-June 1908 (Box 2)
  - George N. Fletcher & Sons
    - Letter book
      - 1895-1898 (Box 3)
      - February-September 1899 (Box 3)
      - 1913-1915 (Box 3)
      - 1917-1923 (Box 3)
    - Plat book 1909 (Box 3)
- Legal files
  The Legal Files Series includes documentation pertaining to litigation mainly involving Fletcher business enterprises.
  - Fletcher Paper Co. vs. Detroit & Mackinac Railroad Company 1911-1912, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fletcher vs. Fletcher
    - Papers 1915-1920 (Box 3)
    - Exhibit materials, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - R.H. Spaulding, administrator vs. George N. Fletcher, et al.
    - Plaintiff's brief
      - v. 1. 1856-April 28, 1873 (Box 4)
      - v. 2. 1856-April 28, 1873 (Box 4)
    - Court proceedings
      - March 31, 1875 (Box 4)
      - June 16, 1876 (Box 4)
      - March 11, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous court materials, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - William White vs. George N. Fletcher
    - Papers 1870s-1890s, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - U.S. vs. Fletcher 1907 (Box 4)
  - Fletcher Paper Co. vs. Alpena Electric Light Co. and Alpena Power Co. Ltd. Papers 1918 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous court cases, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous court exhibits, 10 folders (Box 4)
  - Grant vs. Fletcher
    - Legal briefs and arguments, 7 volumes (Box 5)
    - Transcripts of court proceedings, 1-38 (incomplete) (Box 6)
    - Chronological statement (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous court transcripts (Box 6)
    - Exhibit materials, 1 volumes; 5 folders (Box 6)
- Frank W. Fletcher Personal papers
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - 1903 1914-1918 (Box 6)
      (include letter Feb, 3, 1903 with Albert Kahn; letters, June 8, 1917, June 5, 1918 and June 19, 1918 with Franklin D. Roosevelt)
    - 1919 (Box 6)
    - 1920-1922 (Box 6)
    - 1926 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence re. U-M Board of Regents 1918-1919 (Box 6)
      (include correspondence with Marion L. Burton)
    - Correspondence re. U-M Board of Regents 1920-1924 (Box 6)
      (concerning in part visit of Robert Frost to U-M in 1922)
    - Papers re. Charles Mullen 1909-1913 (Box 6)
    - Papers re. Charles Mullen 1914-1919 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with Chase Osborn 1917-1919 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with Chase Osborn 1920-1922 (Box 6)
  - Estate papers (George Fletcher) (Box 6)
  - Estate papers (Frank W. Fletcher) (Box 6)
  - Estate papers (John J. Foley) (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 6)
Related material
The research should note that related collections of records have been received and are separated cataloged. These include the Thunder River Boom Company, the Fletcher, Pack & Company Records, the Frank W. Fletcher papers, and the Gilchrist Family papers. The Frank W. Fletcher papers relate mainly to his service as a Regent of the University of Michigan.